<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true reporte of the great ouerthrowe lately giuen vnto the Spaniards, in their resolute assault of Bergen op Zoam, in the lowe countries</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119244</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854451</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854451</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19873</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08696)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19873)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1195:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true reporte of the great ouerthrowe lately giuen vnto the Spaniards, in their resolute assault of Bergen op Zoam, in the lowe countries</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12]+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. E[ld] and are to be sold by Iohn Hodgets at his shop in Pauls church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B³+ (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 1900a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks all after leaf B3.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bergen op Zoom (Netherlands) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19873:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 26 -->
            <p>A True Reporte of the Great ouerthrowe lately <hi>giuen vnto the Spaniards in their</hi> reſolute aſſault of BERGEN OP ZOAM, in the Lowe Countries.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON <hi>Printed by</hi> G. E. <hi>and are to be ſold by</hi> Iohn Hodgets <hi>at his ſhop in Pauls church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1605.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19873:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 27 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:19873:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 27 -->
            <head>The copie of a Letter ſent from a Gentleman to his worſhipfull friend in England, containing a true report of the Aſlault giuen vpon <hi>Bergen op Zoam</hi> by the enemy the 19. of September laſt paſt, in the night. 1605.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Elbeloued Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>you ſhal vnderſtand by theſe my letters, what courſe the Enemie tooke ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lately to aſſault our Towne of <hi>Bergen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On Monday beeing the ninetene day of September laſt, about 2. of the clocke in the night, the Enemie came before the Towne, and ſettled his Forces in a place called <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were of them fiue thouſand Foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="tcp:19873:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->My Maiſters, it had beene better for you to haue gone on pilgrimage, and viſited our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, Saint <hi>Mary Acuti-collis,</hi> for here the Goodman of the houſe is at home, and here is meate inough for you ready dreſſed: here is a little ſawce for you, but it is very ſharpe, yet if you lacke Beere, we haue inough laid in for you againſt your comming: thoſe knaues thoſe theeues, your leaders and commaunders haue brought you hither to the ſlaughter (take heed all your throates be not cut, before you depart.) This was the common note and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall cries that we ſent them, which they might heare very eaſily euery word.</p>
            <p>Whiles wee thus laboured to call vnto them, and were buſied in diſcharging our Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinace vpon them, the enemy had ſet a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarre to the gate which was next to the towne, for with a ladder which was an hundred foote longe, (which they could drawe out in length or ſhorten, as occaſion ſhould require) they had gotten paſſage ouer the Flood gates, when the fire brake out of the Petarre, it came with ſuch a force, that all the barres flowe out of their holds, the gates were ſhaken open, and the drawe bridge fell downe, I ſtanding aloft, thought that the whole gate had fallen, there
<pb facs="tcp:19873:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 28 -->were ſuch a number of Tyles and ſtones that flewe in our faces. Then the enemie gaue a horrible ſhowte, to encourage one another that they might haue entred the Towne at one puſhe: but wee immediately came downe from the wales with might and maine and foreſtalled them, making all the prouiſion we could to hinder their entry; ſo little did we deſire to haue their company.</p>
            <p>There is another gate in the Towne, which is not very ſtrong, wherefore to helpe that, we brought and laide to it the greateſt peeces of tymber that wee could gette, and trees, and wagons, and whatſoeuer came firſt to hand, and in the end wee digged vp the ſtones and pauements in the ſtreete, and heaped them together to hinder their entry.</p>
            <p>Our men that tarried yet aboue, hurled downe ſtones, and caſt fire vpon them, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the meanes they could deuiſe for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, as the preſent occaſion and vrgent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity required.</p>
            <p>In the ende, about a quarter of an howre after this, they were ſo ſcarr'd and frighted, that for feare they began to retyre; but they that had next place vnto the Gate and came firſt thither, had much adoe to gette out, for they that came after kept them ſo faſte in that
<pb facs="tcp:19873:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->they could not eaſily turne backe againe.</p>
            <p>In the ende when they ſaw our reſolution, that they were thus manfully reſiſted by al the meanes that might bee deuiſed, they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced with their great dammage, and loſſe of many Souldiers, to ſhift for their liues, and get away.</p>
            <p>In the meane time wee drew vp the Bridge againe, and fortified that Gate by which they intended to haue entred with their Horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p>When they ſawe this, that they had ſpent all their time here to ſo little purpoſe, they made in all haſte toward the water ſide, vnto the place where they had beene before: ſo did they alſo to the Northwarde, and manie went with their Bridges and other prouiſion to the Southwarde.</p>
            <p>But when they ſawe ſuch good prouiſion vpon the ſodaine, and ſo great fortifications, both in the Bulwarke, and in the place which is commonly called <hi>De Polder,</hi> beyond all mens expectation, they left their bridge behind them, with their Dragges and other warlike prouiſion, togither with a company of their men ſlaine, to the number of two and twentie, and ſo flew away.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19873:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 29 -->
The Petarre which they had faſtened vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Gate which is towarde <hi>Sattenhimbuſe</hi> to blowe it open, brake not, but they had laide Bridges there, by which ſome of them had gotten paſſage ouer; But in the meane ſpace, we were ſo ſharpe ſette, and came vpon them with ſuch violence, that with the loſſe of ten men onely, wee enforced them to retire, in more haſte then they came thither, and then wee heard it ſtrike foure of the clocke, but before the hindmoſt of them were gone, it was almoſt fiue of the clocke, ſuch was their amazement, and ſo little minde they had to tarrie one for another.</p>
            <p>Thinke with your ſelfe nowe good Sir, howe wee were toiled and wearied from two of the clocke till this time, I my ſelfe was ſo moiled and wette, as if I had beene but newely drawne out of the Riuer.</p>
            <p>But God bee bleſſed, who alwaies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth his people, and hath thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued vs from the handes of ſuch blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and mercileſſe people, and gaue ſuch boldneſſe and courage vnto our whole Companie, as I would neuer haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued it, if that I had not ſeene it:
<pb facs="tcp:19873:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 30 -->For both the Citizens and the Souldiers were ſo valiant in fight &amp; ſo reſolute to die, if neede had beene, as it was verie ſtrange to behold.</p>
            <p>In this exploit the women alſo plaied their parts, (for the cuſtome of that ſexe) for they brought vs great abundance of ſtrawe, which we preſently ſet on fire, and caſte downe ouer the wales, whereby we were the better able in the darkenes of the night to diſcerne the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie at the wales and about the gate.</p>
            <p>Wee were much holpen alſo by the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troppes &amp; pitchbals, which we caſt abroad &amp; ſcattered here and there. And this alſo was a worthy ſight, to behold how the women and the children little and great, young and olde, one with another, came to the Wales, where the greateſt trouble was, and ſpake moſt cheerefully to vs, and asked vs, ſaying, well done my heartes: what, doe yee lacke any thing? do ye want any powder, or ſhorte, or matches? or any thing that may doe you, and our Towne good? and they brought vs alſo a great number of Baskets full of ſtones; that euery man might haue ſomewhat to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them withall.</p>
            <p>Many alſo brought vs the ſtrawe that was for the horſe litters, when they ſawe what vſe we had of it: and others brought vs ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance
<pb facs="tcp:19873:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 30 -->of Beere, that we were not able to drawe it all out, and drinke it. This kindneſſe and liberalitie pleaſed the Souldiers very well, who couragiouſly cried out continually, and encouraged the Towneſmen, ſaying: be of good cheere, ye honeſt Citizens; bee of good comfort, and haue a good heart, and then the day began to breake, and we had ſome light; which we were very glad of.</p>
            <p>The enemies, as wee were giuen to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand afterward, had not an end of their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles thus, but were put to the ſword, and ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for the ſpace of three daies after.</p>
            <p>Nowe bleſſed be God; we had but one man ſlaine, and he was a common Souldier: ſixe only were wounded, and the moſt hurt that was done, was done by Gunne powder.</p>
            <p>There were of the Enemies ſlaine three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and ten, whereof many were of their beſt and chiefeſt men, and principall officers.</p>
            <p>The Enemy, as we vnderſtood by the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen of the countrie, and the intelligence that was giuen to the Gouernour of the towne, carried away ſixe and thirty Wagons loaden with dead men, and ſuch as were wounded in the attempt: ſo that we may bee certainly aſſured that hee loſt then at the leaſt a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19873:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 31 -->
When the Souldiers of their ſide heard that they were determined to make his attempt vpon the Towne of <hi>Bergen,</hi> they had much a do to drawe them to the Towne, they were ſo loath to come there: fearing their welcome: at laſt for their better inducement, they gaue out ſpeeches, that the greateſt part of the Towne was confederate with them, and would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ioyne, but in the end, the euent fell out otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>We doe not as yet certainely knowe how manie of their heades and chiefe commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the enemy are ſlaine: they haue left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde them many of their Ladders, Bridges and Wagons couered with Leather or Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſſe, and much other ſuch baggage.</p>
            <p>There came a meſſenger but euen now vnto the towne, who bringeth newes that their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall hath both his legges ſtroken off with a peece of Ordinance; and that many of their principal officers are either ſlaine or wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded.</p>
            <p>Some of them were driuen into the water, and ſo drowned: So that as yet wee haue no certaine intelligence what number of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ſlaine, but ſo manie as wee can finde in ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places, diſperſed, amount to the number of three ſcore and ten.</p>
            <p>The Gouernour of the Towne gaue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſword
<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19873:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 31 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
